Guide to the 1925 F Street Club Collection, 1933-1999 MS2360.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
1925 F Street Club Collection
circa 1933 -circa 1999
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2360.UA
4.75 Linear Feet Four document boxes, one record center box, one flat box
The 1925 F Street Club was one of the most exclusive social clubs in Washington, D.C. during the 20th century. This collection contains, guest lists, correspondences, financial records, operational records, event documents, and publicity materials of the club. The materials in the collection range in dates from circa 1933-circa 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
The materials are divided into five series: Financial Records, Club Management Documents, Club Events, Publicity, and Materials from Dr. Richard H. "Dick" Howland.
Biographical / Historical
The F Street Club was once called "the hardest door in Washington to open" because of its elite status as the premier social club in the district. The private social club was started in 1933 by Laura Merriam Curtis Gross and was managed by Gross until her death in 1973. Gross was the uncrowned queen of the Republican party during her lifetime, so many of the clubs were powerful members of that party. However, in the later part of the twentieth century, more and more people of the Democratic party joined the club as well.
The club could accommodate about 48 people for dinner, and it became renowned for its intimate setting. Presidents such as Gerald Ford and Ronald Reagan held parties at the club, and many more influential Washingtonians hosted and attended functions at the club.
Before becoming the F Street Club, the house was originally built for U.S. Navy Admiral, Charles Steedman in 1849. Its next owner was local businessman, Alexander Ray, whose family owned the house from 1868 until it was purchased by American University around 1920 to be used a downtown campus for the institution. When those plans did not quickly come to fruition, the university rented the house to Mrs. Gross who lived in it for a little over ten years before transforming it into the famous social club. The George Washington University purchased the house from American University, which still officially owned the property, in 1974; however, it continued to lease the property to the club. In 1999, the club disbanded, and the house became the Alumni House for GWU. President Knapp, the university's president, moved into the house in 2008, and it remains the official residence of the president of GWU.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, meeting minutes, personnel files, financial records, programs, brochures, menus, photographs, guest dining schedules, and publicity materials. The material dates from 1933-1999. These are the records of the 1925 F Street Club, a prominent social club in Washington, D.C. during the twentieth century.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Exact acquisition date and source are unknown, although it is believed that most of this collection came to the archives in 2008 when the building was turned into the President's Residence. (Previously accession 751)
The acquisition date and source for Series 5 is unknown.
- Club Management, circa 1939-circa 1999; 1; 4 Linear Feet Files in this series are located in two document boxes, one record center box, and one flat box.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials related to the managment of the club. Files include materials that refer to topics like board meetings, memberships lists, correspondences between the club and its members, the physical club and its maintenance, and guest attendance calnedars. These materials are from circa 1939 to circa 1999. These are part of the records of the 1925 F Street Club, a prominent social club in Washington, D.C. during the twentieth century.
  - Membership List, 1 December 1982; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1925 F Street Club Closing Materials, 22 May 1997; Series 1; 2 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 2, Folder 3)
  - Membership Lists and Brief Club History, 1997-1998; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Round Table, 1979-1994; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1972, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board and Meeting Minutes, July 1933-14 May 1997; Series 1; 7 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 7, Folder 8, Folder 9, Folder 10, Folder 11, Folder 12, Folder 13)
  - Membership List, 19 June 1997; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General Correspondences 1930s-1940s, 1933-1939; Series 1; 2 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 1, Folder 2)
  - F.A.L.Con Inc. (Food and Lodging Consultation Incorporated) Correspondences, 1979-1980; Series 1; 2 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 3, Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Food and Service Inspections and ABC Licenses, 1971-1987; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Houseware-S. Freedman and Sons, 1973-1984; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Housewares-China, 1974-1978; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Housewares-Beverages, 1973-1980; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Housewares-Silver, 1967-1981; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Housewares-Linen, 25 August 1971; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Housewares-Glassware, 1975; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Furniture Inventory and Value Assesment, 1977-1993; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gross Estate, 1971-1975; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Certificate of Corporate Resolution, 13 May 1971; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Proposals for Membership, 31 January 1984; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Indenture of Lease, 18 November 1981; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence 1950s, 1950-1959; Series 1; 2 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondences with The George Washington University, 1973-1978; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - George Washington University 1980s-Rental of Building, 1980-1983; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Proposed Membership Lists, 1985; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Maintenance, 10 October 1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Maintenance-Roof and Windows, 1977-1985; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Maintenance-Pest Control, 1982; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Maintenance-Painting, 1984-1986; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Maintenance-Window Proposal, 9 September 1985; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Maintenance-Kitchen Equipment, 1972-1982; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Maintenance-Garden, 1980-1983; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Maintenance-Air Conditioning and Boiler, 1977-1984; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Staff-Salaries and Job Benefits, 1974-1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Staff-Part-Time Staff, 1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Staff-Regular Staff, 1980-1984; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Guest Attendance Calendar, 1957-1962; Series 1; 5 folder(s) (Box 5, Item 1, Item 2, Item 3, Item 4, Item 5)
  - Corporate Seal, 1933; Series 1 (Box 5, Item 6)
- Financial Records, circa 1939-circa 1999; 2; .75 Linear Feet The files in this series are held in two document boxes.
  The materials in this series relate to the financials of the 1925 F Street Club. Materials included are account audit reports, club account balance sheets, asset and spending reports, and house charges. The materials range in date from circa 1939 to circa 1999. These are part of the records of the 1925 F Street Club, a prominent social club in Washington, D.C. during the twentieth century.
  - Account Audit Reports, 1933-1937; Series 2; 2 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 15, Folder 16)
  - Asset and Spending Reports, April 1979-March 1980; Series 2; 3 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 17, Folder 18, Folder 19)
  - Account Reports and General Ledgers, 1967-1968; Series 2; 4 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 20, Folder 21, Folder 22, Folder 23)
  - Balance Sheet and Schedules, March 1978-31 March 1984; Series 2; 3 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 24, Folder 25, Folder 26)
  - Accounts Receivable Listing, 1986-1987; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sales Analysis, 1 January 1970-April 1995; Series 2; 2 folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 2, Folder 3)
  - Delinquent House Charges, 1979-1980; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Club Events, circa 1939- circa 1999; 3; .5 Linear Feet The three files in this series can be found in one document box.
  The files in this series contain matieral srelated to specific events held at the club. Matierals include menus, seating charts, photographs, programs, and correspondences regarding certain events. The matierals range in date from circa 1939 to circa 1999. These are part of the records of the 1925 F Street Club, a prominent social club in Washington, D.C. during the twentieth century.
  - Event Photos, Undated; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Event Documents for the IMF (International Monetary Fund), 1983-1986; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Event Materials, 1985-1990; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Publicity, circa 1939-circa 1999; 4; 3.5 Linear Feet Files from this series are located in one records center box, one document box, and one flat box.
  The materials in this series pertain to the publicity of the club. Files includes materials such as photographs of staff and members, correspondences with the National Club Association and other clubs nationwide, articles about the club or related clubs in news outlets like the Washington Post or The Washingtonian. Materials in this series range in dates from circa 1939 to circa 1999. These are part of the records of the 1925 F Street Club, a prominent social club in Washington, D.C. during the twentieth century.
  - Related Clubs, 1980-1985; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Articles of The Washingtonian, March 1984-1986; Series 4 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Michael Jaslyn-Manager (Retired July 1981), Undated; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified Photo, Undated; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified Photo of a Woman, Undated; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Materials from Dr. Richard H. "Dick" Howland, 1961-1997, and undated; Series 5; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box (Box 6)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  The acquisition of the materials in this series is unknown, but they appear to have belonged to Richard H. "Dick" Howland. They were discovered in a Gelman Library office in 2017.
  This series consists of materials that appear to have been generated and collected by Dr. Richard H. "Dick" Howland during his association with the 1925 F. Street Club. They concern sales of items that were in the house, general club history, and the transition of the property to GW.
  - Photographs, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Board meeting materials, 1997 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Pauline Hollingsworth, 1983-1987, 1997 (Box 6)
  - Appraisal of items in building, 1997 (Box 6)
  - Membership lists and club rules, 1974-1992 (Box 6)
  - Dictaphone recordings, undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence regarding reciprocity with 14 W. Hamilton Street Club, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Clippings and letters to membership regarding potential move due to GW not extending lease, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Clippings and club histories, undated (Box 6)
  - History of 1925 F Street, Compiled by Mrs. Elden Billings Columbia Historical Society, 1961-1963 (Box 6)
  - Information on Alexander Ray, former owner of the house, undated (Box 6)